{
  "title": "Operating_System - Memory_Management — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Memory_Management — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>A processor can support a maximum memory of 4GB, where the memory is word-addressable (a word consists of two bytes). The size of the address bus of the process or is at least bits________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "31",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39632/gate2016-1-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Dirty bit for a page in a page table <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>helps avoid unnecessary writes on a paging device</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>helps maintain LRU information</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>allows only read on a page</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>helps avoid unnecessary writes on a paging device</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2241/gate1997-3-10-isro2008-57-isro2015-64\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Increasing the RAM of a computer typically improves performance because: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Virtual Memory increases</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Larger RAMs are faster</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Fewer page faults occur</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Fewer segmentation faults occur</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Fewer page faults occur</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1358/gate2005-22-isro2015-36\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>If there are 32 segments, each size 1k bytes, then the logical address should have <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>13 bits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>14 bits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>15 bits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>16 bits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>15 bits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/51212/isro2015-31\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>A computer system implements 8 kilobyte pages and a 32-bit physical address space. Each page table entry contains a valid bit, a dirty bit, three permission bits, and the translation. If the maximum size of the page table of a process is 24 megabytes, the length of the virtual address supported by the system is _____ bits. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "36",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8247/gate2015-2-33#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider six memory partitions of sizes 200 KB, 400 KB, 600 KB, 500 KB, 300 KB and 250 KB, where KB refers to kilobyte. These partitions need to be allotted to four processes of sizes 357 KB, 210 KB, 468 KB and 491 KB in that order. If the best fit algorithm is used, which partitions are NOT allotted to any process? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>200 KB and 300 KB</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>200 KB and 250 KB</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>250 KB and 300 KB</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>300 KB and 400 KB</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>200 KB and 300 KB</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8145/gate2015-2-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A computer system implements a 40-bit virtual address, page size of 8 kilobytes, and a 128-entry translation look-aside buffer (TLB) organized into 32 sets each having four ways. Assume that the TLB tag does not store any process id. The minimum length of the TLB tag in bits is _________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "22",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8120/gate2015-2-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Consider a main memory with five page frames and the following sequence of page references: 3, 8, 2, 3, 9, 1, 6, 3, 8, 9, 3, 6, 2, 1, 3. Which one of the following is true with respect to page replacement policies First In First Out (FIFO) and Least Recently Used (LRU)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both incur the same number of page faults</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>FIFO incurs 2 more page faults than LRU</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>LRU incurs 2 more page faults than FIFO</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>FIFO incurs 1 more page faults than LRU</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Both incur the same number of page faults</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8353/gate2015-1-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider a system with byte-addressable memory, 32-bit logical addresses, 4 kilobyte page size and page table entries of 4 bytes each. The size of the page table in the system in megabytes is ________ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8186/gate2015-1-19#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>What is the size of the physical address space in a paging system which has a page table containing 64 entries of 11 bit each (including valid and invalid bit) and a page size of 512 bytes? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(2^{11}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{15}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{19}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^{20}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{19}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52224/isro2014-77\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Dirty bit is used to indicate which of the following? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A page fault has occurred</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A page has corrupted data</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A page has been modified after being loaded into cache</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>An illegal access of page</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>A page has been modified after being loaded into cache</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/55089/isro2014-70\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>A computer has 16 pages of virtual address space but the size of main memory is only four frames. Initially the memory is empty. A program references the virtual pages in the order 0, 2, 4, 5, 2, 4, 3, 11, 2, 10. How many page faults occur if LRU page replacement algorithm is used? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>8</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/54972/isro2014-44\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Using the page table shown below, translate the physical address 25 to virtual address. The address length is 16 bits and page size is 2048 words while the size of the physical memory is four frames.<br>\\(\\begin{array}{lcc} \\text { Page } &amp; \\text { Present }(1-In , 0-Out) &amp; \\text { Frame } \\\\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 3 \\\\ 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 \\\\ 2 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\\\ 3 &amp; 0 &amp; - \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>25</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>6169</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2073</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4121</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>4121</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/46107/isro2014-35\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following segment table in segmentation scheme :<br>\\(\\begin{array}{|l|l|l|} \\hline \\text { Segment ID } &amp; \\text { Base } &amp; \\text { Limit } \\\\ \\hline 0 &amp; 200 &amp; 200 \\\\ \\hline 1 &amp; 5000 &amp; 1210 \\\\ \\hline 2 &amp; 1527 &amp; 498 \\\\ \\hline 3 &amp; 2500 &amp; 50 \\\\ \\hline \\end{array}\\)<br>What happens if the logical address requested is - Segment Id 2 and offset 1000? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Fetches the entry at the physical address 2527 for segment Id 2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A trap is generated</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Deadlock</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Fetches the entry at offset 27 in Segment Id 3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>A trap is generated</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/16942/isro2014-18\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Consider a paging hardware with a TLB. Assume that the entire page table and all the pages are in the physical memory. It takes 10 milliseconds to search the TLB and 80 milliseconds to access the physical memory. If the TLB hit ratio is 0.6, the effective memory access time (in milliseconds) is _________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "122",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2067/gate2014-3-33#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}